Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - GOETHE, JOHANN WOLFGANG VON, 1749-1832
    - Lyric Poetry
      - Dauer im Wechsel - Goethe, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 247)
        Begins: I was so deeply blest!
        The ms. was addressed by S. M.
        d'Ossoli to John S. Dwight in 1838.
        It was intended, but did not appear
        in Dwight's Select Minor Poems,
        Boston, 1839.
      - The earlking. Goethe, 1895 Mar (Box 8, Folder 248)
        2 l.; 27 cm.
        English translation by Frank Claudy
        of "Der Erlkönig" by Johann Wolfgang
        von Goethe.
        Ms. in hand of translator.
      - The erl king. Goethe, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 249)
        AMs (2 versions), 2 p.; 32 x 20 cm.,
        4 p.; 20 x 13 cm.
        Translation by John Greenleaf
        Whittier (1807-92) of Goethe's poem
        Der Erlkönig.
        The smaller of the 2 mss. is the
        first draft.
        William A. Speck edited the poem for
        publication in the Goethe Jahrbuch,
        1904.
      - Erlkönig, Hannover, Germany, 1898 Jul 29 (Box 8, Folder 250)
        AMs, 2 l.; 18 x 16 cm.
        English translation of Goethe's poem.
        Translated by Anson Phelps Stokes.
        Enclosure: TLS from Anson Phelps
        Stokes to William A. Speck, Feb. 19,
        1924, forwarding this text, with
        envelope.
      - Die Feier des siebenten November 1825, dankbar zu erwiedern, Weimar, 1829 Oct (Box 8, Folder 251)
        1 p.; 12 x 19 cm.
        Printed poem.
        With Goethe's signature and ms. note:
        "erneut Weimar Oktbr. 1829."
        Autograph note at head of page: "This
        leaf I have received out of Goethe[!]
        own hand. J.A. Stumpff. Oct. 17th
        1829. Weimar."
        With: ALS from W.H. Koller, Feb. 21,
        1837, to Mrs. Wilde, sending on this
        item as a gift; with address.
      - The fisher, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 252)
        1 p.; 22 x 25 cm.
        Autograph poem, signed C.T.B.
        Translation of Goethe's Der Fischer.
        Translated by Charles Timothy Brooks.
        With an explanatory note at head of
        page.
        This version differs markedly from
        that printed in Specimens of Foreign
        Standard Literature, ed. by George
        Ripley, 1842 and reprinted in German
        lyric poetry, a collection of songs
        and ballads, 1863.
      - Fräulein Ulrike von Pogwisch, Weimar, 1824 Oct 29 (Box 8, Folder 253)
        1 p.; 23 x 20 cm.
        Autograph poem.
        Unpublished.-Pierre Beres sales list.
        In honor of the 20th birthday of
        Ottilie von Goethe's sister, Ulrike
        von Pogwisch.
      - Den funfzehn englischen Freunden, Weimar, 1831 Aug 28 (Box 8, Folder 254)
        1 p.; 20 x 23 cm.
        Autograph ms., signed
        Poem beginning: Worte, die der
        Dichter spricht.
        Addressed to William Fraser, editor of
        the Magazine for Town and Country.
        Personal, red attached seal with motto:
        Ohne Hast, Aber Ohne Rast.
        First pub. with title An die neunzehn
        Freunde in England, in the periodical
        Chaos, No. 6, Jahrg. 2. Also pub. as
        no. 2 of Facsimiles and reproductions
        of unique and rare items from the
        William A. Speck Collection of
        Goetheana.
        With: Facsimile of the Chaos number
        containing the printed text
        photographed with this is the ms.
        apparently given to Ottilie von
        Goethe for the Chaos, with title
        written in by Eckermann: An die
        Neunzehn Freunde in England.
      - Klarster Stimme, froh an Sinn, 1831 (Box 8, Folder 255)
        2 p.; 34 x 21 cm.
        Autograph ms., in pencil.
        Rough draft of his poem entitled Der
        Demoiselle Schmehling nach Aufführung
        des Hassischen Sta. Elena al
        Calvario. Leipzig 1771. The second
        stanza has title: An Madame Mara zum
        frohen Jahresfeste. Weimar 1831. Both
        stanzas were written in 1831.
        Written on a discarded leaf of a letter
        to Goethe, one side already had been
        used by him for jotting down some
        notes. The text is almost
        indecipherable.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe, v. 4,
        p. 298.
      - The metamorphosis of plants, n.d.
        - AMs, 6 l. numb. 230a, 232a, 234a, 236a, 238a, 240a; 11 x 21 cm. Translation, by William Whewell, of Goethe's poem Die Metamorphose der Pflanzen. Begins: Thou, my love, are perplexed.
        - IN: English hexameter translations from Schiller, Göthe, Homer, Callinus, and Meleager, London 1847. (Hd a847). The printed book includes German and English text of this work; each ms. leaf is tipped in between the appropriate pages of both texts.
      - Goethe's "Mignon," a "Paradise lost" poem, translated by H. P. Spring, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 256)
        1 l.; 30 cm.
        Ms. in unidentified hand.
      - Know'st thou the land where the pale citrons blow? (Box 8, Folder 257)
        1 p.; 18 cm.
        Autograph ms., signed, translation of
        Goethe's poem Mignon, stanzas 1 & 2.
        Translated by Samuel Taylor Coleridge.
        A different version of stanza 1, dated
        1799?, is printed in The complete
        poetical works of Samuel Taylor
        Coleridge, Oxford, 1912, v. 1,
        p. 311.
      - Ein Quidam sagt: ich bin von keiner Schule, 1812 Nov 4 (Box 9, Folder 258)
        Autograph poem, signed G.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe with title:
        Den Originalen.
      - Wenn der Freund auf lichtem Grunde, Weimar, 1828 Jan 1 (Box 9, Folder 259)
        On pink card; 8 x 11 cm., within
        embossed leaf border.
        Autograph poem, signed.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe with heading:
        An Frau Carlyle, Weimar, den 27.
        December 1827[!]
        A stickpin with medallion portrait of
        Goethe is affixed; both poems in a
        leather case with gilt lettering:
        Greeting to Thomas Carlyle from
        Goethe 1828.
        With: Another greeting card with poem:
        Wenn Phoebus Rosse sich zu schnell.
        On card; 13 x 9 cm., within gold
        leaf border. Autograph poem, signed,
        with heading: Den lieben treuen
        Edinburger Gatten zum Neuenjahre
        1828. Printed in Weimar Ausgabe with
        heading: An Frau Clementine von
        Mandelsloh, with date Weimar, am
        kürzesten Tage 1827.
      - The bliss of sorrow, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 260)
        Autograph poem, a translation of
        Goethe's Wonne der Wehmut.
        Translated by Edgar Alfred Bowring.
        Printed in Bowring's "The poems of
        Goethe ...", London, 1853.
        With: Autograph poem, "The Child in the
        Cradle," trans. of Schiller's Das
        Kind in der Wiege, signed by Bowring,
        1 p.; 12 x 18 cm., on same page as
        above; personal, impressed seal.
    - Autograph Quotations
      - AMs, signed, quotation from Goethe, 1860 Jan 19 (Box 9, Folder 261)
        "To give room for wandering, is it,
        that the world was made so wide,"
        translation by Bayard Taylor of "Dass
        wir uns in ihr zerstreuen, darum ist
        die Welt so gross"; last 2 lines from
        Wanderlied aus Wilhelm Meisters
        Wanderjahren.
      - Empty folder (Box 9, Folder 262)
      - Es ist dafür gesorgt dass die Bäume nicht in den Himmel wachsen, Weimar, 1814 Jan 17
        - Autograph quotation, signed. Leaf from an autograph book, with gilt edge. Matted; mat with colored floral border. Motto of the third book of Dichtung und Wahrheit.
        - See: Oversize: Box 19, folder 831a
      - Der Verstand durchdringt wohl alles ... (Box 9, Folder 263)
        1 p.; 16 x 9 cm.
        Autograph quotation.
        Copy in Friedrich Wilhelm Riemer's
      - Was ist das Heiligste?, London, 1848 May 30 (Box 9, Folder 264)
        AMs, 1 p.; 11 x 18 cm. mounted on a
        page 15 x 24 cm.
        Signed by Christian Karl Josias
        Freiherr von Bunsen.
        From Goethe's Vier Jahreszeiten,
        Herbst.
        Presumably a leaf from an autograph
        With English translation in an
        unidentified hand on the mount.
      - Was man erfindet, thut man mit Liebe..., Weimar. 1813 Dec 29
        - 1 l.; 11 x 18 cm., mounted to 29 x 36 cm. Autograph ms., signed, Goethe. Mounted on black edged pink mat, decorated with birds and flowers; the decoration was done by Alwine Frommann. The autograph was written for the Grandduchess Maria Pavlovna; she in turn gave it to her daughter Augusta, who in 1861 became Queen of Prussia and ten years later the first Empress of Germany. With autograph note, signed, from Augusta to Hofbibliothekar Samuel Heinrich Spiker, on his sixtieth birthday, December 24, 1846, on letter paper with lace border, bearing the Hohenzollern crest.
        - See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 831
      - You are the merriest undone man in Europe, Weimar, 1814 Jan 3 (Box 9, Folder 265)
        Autograph quotation, signed.
        Clearly a leaf from an autograph
        album, with gilt edge.
        On January 7 of the same year, Goethe
        applies the quotation to himself in a
        letter to Von Trebra: "Ich habe keine
        weitere Ambition, als dass man zu mir
        sagen möge: You are ..."
    - Letters
      - ALS (Box 9, Folder 266)
        1 p.; 22 x 18 cm.
        Signed: G.
        In Goethe's handwriting, with note
        in upper left hand corner in
        another hand: "Von Göthen, als er
        wollte, dass ich den Artikel über
        die Aufführung des Hamlets[?]
        unterdrücken sollte."
        In upper right hand corner: "79"
        -- i.e. 1779?
      - LS, Weimar, 1782 Feb 20 (Box 9, Folder 267)
        1 p.; 22 x 20 cm.
        Handwriting not identified.
        Not printed in Weimar Ausgabe.
        Asking the unidentified recipient
        to transmit an enclosed letter
        to Michelangelo Salom at Padua,
        the translator of Werther.
      - ALS: Weimar, to "theuerster Herr und Freund", 1830 Nov 30 (Box 9, Folder 268)
        1 p.; 15 x 23 cm.
        In pencil.
        Not printed in the Weimar Ausgabe.
      - ALS, to Friedrich Justin Bertuch, [1789?] (Box 9, Folder 269)
        1 p.; 19 x 20 cm.
        Deals with the publication of
        Das römische Carnival.
        Beginning of 1789?
        Published in Goethe-Jahrbuch and
        Weimar Ausgabe.
      - LS: Weimar, to Adolf Oswald Blumenthal, 1819 May 28 (Box 9, Folder 270)
        3 p.; 25 x 21 cm.
        In handwriting of Rinaldo Vulpius.
        Suggestions for an edition of German
        poets who write in Latin, which
        Blumenthal is planning to compile.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe, Goethe-
        Jahrbuch II, 1881, and Ungedrucktes
        aus dem Goethe-Kreise, 1896.
      - LS: Weimar, to Karl August Böttiger, 1797 May 17 (Box 9, Folder 271)
        Personal impressed seal.
        In Geist's handwriting.
        Goethe is sending a number of books
        for Böttiger's library of
        numismatics.
      - Correspondence (copies, excerpts) of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe with Graf Carl Friedrich Moritz Paul von Brühl, 1828 (Box 9, Folder 272)
        8 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
        Goethe to Brühl: Jan. 17 & 26, Feb.
        20, 1828; one undated.
        Brühl to Goethe: Jan. 10 & 22, Feb.
        14 & 24, 1828.
        Copied by Friedrich Wilhelm Riemer
        preparatory to his edition of Briefe
        von und an Goethe, hrsg. von F. W.
        Riemer, Leipzig, Weidmann'sche
        Buchhandlung, 1846.
      - LS: Weimar, to Johann Wolfgang Döbereiner, 1813 Mar 10 (Box 9, Folder 273)
        The leaf containing the address is
        edged and mended.
        In the hand of Goethe's secretary
        Heinrich Ernst Weber.
        Döbereiner was apothecary and chemist,
        professor at Jena.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe, Abt. IV,
        v. 23, p. 194.
        Gift of Otto and William C. Madlener,
        1959.
        Related Archival Materials note
        See also: Additions Since 2000, Box 20, folders 833-834
      - LS: Weimar, to John Wolfgang Döbereiner, 1829 Feb 4 (Box 9, Folder 274)
        2 p.; 20 x 20 cm.
        In Johann August Friedrich John's
        The date was changed by a later hand
        from 1824 to 1829.
        Goethe's letter was printed in Weimar
        Ausgabe, from an unsigned first
        draft.
        Enclosure: 2 notes, apparently rough
        labels for geological specimens.
      - LS: Weimar, to Julius J. Elkan, 1829 Aug 19 (Box 9, Folder 275)
        Published from a draft in Weimar
        Ausgabe.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Ludwig Friedrich von Froriep, 1824 Nov (Box 9, Folder 276)
        1 p.; 12 x 14 cm.
        Mounted on blue board and framed.
        Requesting the presence of von
        Froriep and party at the Weimar
        Library on November 25.
      - LS: Jena, to Johann Christian Gädicke?, 1799 Dec 6 (Box 9, Folder 277)
        With a note from Professor E.
        Scheidemantel, Weimar,
        authenticating the note.
      - AL (draft, incomplete): Weimar, to Leopoldine Grustner von Grusdorf, 1827 Mar 30 (Box 9, Folder 278)
        4 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
        Published in Weimar Ausgabe, v. 42,
        p. 107.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Frau Henriette Caroline Friederike (Jagemann) von Heygendorf, 1825 Oct 19 (Box 9, Folder 279)
        1 p.; 20 x 24 cm.
        Printed in the Weimar Ausgabe from
        the rough draft.
      - AL (draft, incomplete): Weimar, to Heinrich Gustav Hotho, 1830 Apr 19 (Box 9, Folder 280)
        2 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
        The Weimar Ausgabe prints a longer
        letter in v. 47, p. 26 from a rough
        draft in Johann August Friedrich
        John's hand. This is probably a
        copy by Riemer in preparation for
        an edition of Goethe's letters:
        Briefe von und an Goethe, Leipzig,
        1846.
      - AL (copy), to Wilhelm von Humboldt, 1831 Dec 1 (Box 9, Folder 281)
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe.
      - ALS: Carls Bad, to Countess Jaraczewska, 1823 Sep 4 (Box 9, Folder 282)
        1 p.; 15 x 11 cm.
        Pencilled on verso: Le Sketz Book
        de Wasingnton Irving.
        With this note, Goethe is returning
        the Sketch Book, which Countess
        Jaraczewska had lent him.
      - ALS: Teplitz, to Ernst Carl Christian John, 1813 Aug 9 (Box 9, Folder 283)
        1 p.; 17 x 21 cm.
        John was Goethe's secretary, 1812-14.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Franz Kirms, 1812 Mar 7 (Box 9, Folder 284)
        1 p.; 18 x 23 cm.
        Published in Weimar Ausgabe.
        Deals with arrangements entered into
        between Goethe and Iffland in regard
        to the production of Goethe's
        revision of Romeo and Juliette.
      - ALS: Weimar?, to Karl Ludwig von Knebel, 1809 (Box 9, Folder 285)
        Endorsed by H.C. Robinson, London,
        Dec. 1832.
      - LS: Weimar, to Gottlob Wilhelm Kühn, 1816 May 30 (Box 9, Folder 286)
        3 p.; 20 x 23 cm.
        In Kräuter's handwriting.
        Except for a postscript, the letter
        is printed in Weimar Ausgabe.
      - LS: Weimar, to Heinrich Luden, 1806 Dec 26 (Box 9, Folder 287)
        1 p.; 23 c 19 cm.
        Concerns the translation of Ugo
        Foscolo's Jacopo Ortis and the
        novel Sydner ou Les dangers de
        l'imagination by Mauritian author
        Barthélemy Huet de Froberville
        (1761-1835).
      - ALS, to Johann Heinrich Meyer, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 288)
        1 p.; 10 x 13 cm.
        Within ornamental border.
      - LS: Jena, to Johann Heinrich Meyer, 1819 Aug 16 (Box 9, Folder 289)
        Two official red seals attached.
        In the handwriting of Johann August
        Friedrich John.
      - AL (draft, incomplete): Karlsbad?, to Adam Müller, 1807 Aug 28 (Box 9, Folder 290)
        3 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
        Apparently the ms. for the printed
        letter in Riemer's "Briefe von und
        an Goethe", p. 169. Not in Weimar
      - LS: Weimar, to Franz Heinrich Müller, 1829 Jan 10 (Box 9, Folder 291)
        Within black border.
      - LS: Weimar, to Georg Heinrich Noehden, London, 1820 Mar 6 (Box 9, Folder 292)
        3 p.; 25 x 20 cm.
        Concerning Goethe's work on the Last
        Supper by Leonardo da Vinci which
        Noehden translated into English.
        Mounted at end of letter a pen and ink
        drawing representing a medal showing
        Karl August's head in profile on the
        obverse and Leonardo da Vinci's and
        Bossi's on the reverse.
      - LS: Schloss Dornburg, to Henriette Ottilie Ulrike Freifrau von Pogwisch, geborene Gräfin Henckel von Donnersmarck, 1828 Jul 18 (Box 9, Folder 293)
        2 p.; 22 x 13 cm.
        Letter within mourning border.
        Concerning the return of the book
        "Geschichte der Neugriechen" and the
        order of two others for the Weimar
        Library.
      - LS: Weimar, to [Wilhelm Reichel?], 1829 Feb 14 (Box 9, Folder 294)
        1 p.; 12 x 21 cm.
        Letter within black border. In Johann
        Christian Schuchardt's handwriting.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe from the
      - LS: to Wilhelm Reichel, 1828 Feb 15 (Box 9, Folder 294a)
        1 p.; 16 x 20 cm.
        Letter in secretarial hand. Date on
        verso, 18 Feb. 1828, possibly in
        Charles Frederick Johnson's hand.
      - 2 AL (copy, excerpt): Weimar, to Karl Friedrich Graf von Reinhard, 1828 Jan 27 (Box 9, Folder 295)
        1831 Sep 7
        3 p.; 20 x 34 cm.
        Both letters printed in full in the
        Weimar Ausgabe, the first under the
        date of January 28.
        This is clearly material for a
        contemplated edition of Goethe's
        letters.
      - 7 LS: Weimar, to Therese Albertine Louise (von Jakob) Robinson, 1824 (Box 9, Folder 296)
        Letters dated: Apr. 25 (2 p.); May 11
        (2 p.); Jul. 10 (3 p.); Aug. 2
        (4 p.); Sep. 8 (2 p.); Dec. 4 (2 p.)
        and Dec. 15 (1 p.).
        Letter of Sep. 8 with enclosure: Sep.
        2, Weimar "Serbische Gedichte wären
        nach meiner Ansicht folgendermassen
        zu ordnen", 4 p., signed.
        In the handwriting of Goethe's
        secretary, Johann August Friedrich
        John.
        With English translations, typed.
        All are printed in the Weimar Ausgabe.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Friedrich Ludwig Schröder, 1791 May 24 (Box 9, Folder 297)
        2 p.; 24 x 21 cm.
        Concerning the administration of the
        box office at the Weimar theater
        and the engagement of an actress.
        Printed in the Weimar Ausgabe.
      - AL (copy, fragment), to Christoph Ludwig Friedrich Schultz, 1831 Dec 6 (Box 9, Folder 298)
        1 p.; 21 x 33 cm.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Auguste von Stolberg, 1777 Jul 17 (Box 9, Folder 299)
        Includes the four line poem Alles
        geben Götter die unendlichen ...
      - 7 LS: Weimar, to Johann Friedrich Unger, 1798-1803 (Box 9, Folder 300)
        11 p.; various sizes
        Letters dated: Jan. 30, 1798; Aug. 5,
        1799; Nov. 4, 1799; Mar. 3, 1800
        Apr. 2, 1800; Apr. 10, 1800 and Jun.
        8, 1803.
        All in the handwriting of Goethe's
        secretary Ludwig Geist.
        The first six letters concern the
        publication of Goethe's Neue
        Schriften, Berlin, J.F. Unger, 1792-
        1800, 7 vols. The last is a letter of
        thanks for Unger's gift of a copy of
        Chr. E. von Kleists Sämtliche Werke.
        All printed in Weimar Ausgabe.
        With: Two letters from Bernhard Suphan
        to Prof. K. Budde in Bonn, dated May
        27, 1888 and July 11, 1888.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Christian Gottlob von Voigt, 1811 May 4 (Box 9, Folder 301)
        With autograph statement by Edmund
        Kräuter on verso, verifying that
        the letter is in Goethe's hand.
        Printed in the Weimarer Ausgabe, 4
        (22, p. 390).
        In case, and cardboard cover with
        printed transcription.
      - ALS: Weimar, to Christian Gottlob von Voigt, 1813 Dec 14 (Box 9, Folder 302)
        2 p.; 24 x 20 cm.
        Printed in Weimar Ausgabe and in
        Goethes Briefe an Christian Gottlob
        von Voigt, hrsg. von Otto Jahn,
        Leipzig, 1868.
      - LS: Weimar, to Christian Ernst Friedrich Weller, 1826 Mar 24 (Box 9, Folder 303)
        Handwriting possibly by Heinrich
        Ernst Weber.
      - AL: Weimar, to Black Young & Young, booksellers, London, 1829 Nov 19 (Box 9, Folder 304)
    - Documents
      - Autograph entry from lending list of the Weimarer Landesbibliothek, signed, Weimar, 1830 Oct 4 (Box 9, Folder 305)
        1 p. mounted on cardboard; 8 x 16 cm.
        The request is for Buffon, George Louis
        Leclerc, comte de: Histoire naturelle
        générale et particulière, Paris 1753,
        v. 4 [Quadrupèdes].
        Cf. Keudell, E.v., Goethe als Benutzer
        der Weimarer Bibliothek, 1931, item
        2158.
      - Autograph note, signed, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 306)
        1 p.; 13 x 17 cm.
        Written on verso of a fragment of a
        larger manuscript which is in a
        different hand.
        Endorsing Christian August Vulpius as
        the author of a proposed book.
      - Autograph note, signed G., Weimar, 1831 Oct 24 (Box 10, Folder 307)
        1 p.; 11 x 13 cm.
        Heading: No. 2.
        A request for three books.
      - Autograph signature "ergebenst Goethe", Weimar, 1819 Jan 20 (Box 10, Folder 308)
        8 x 20 cm.
        With envelope "Goethe Handschrift
        unter einem Geschäftsbrief an
        Buchhändler Frommann in Jena."
        Pencilled on back of envelope:
        Handwriting on envelope Alwine
        Frommann, friend of Goethe.
      - Autographa [printed list of names] Mit Bitte um gefällige Beiträge, Weimar, 1811 Dec 20 (Box 10, Folder 309)
        Signed: J W v Goethe
      - Document, signed: Weimar, to "Fürstliche Regierung zu Weimar", 1780 Oct 12 (Box 10, Folder 310)
        2 p.; 33 x 20 cm.
        Co-signers: Freiherr von Fritsch and
        C.F.? Schmauss.
      - Document, signed: Weimar, to "Die Fürstliche Regierung zu Eisenach", 1782 Sep 24 (Box 10, Folder 311)
        2 p.; 20 x 33 cm.
        Co-signer: C.F. Schmauss.
        Concerns remission of certain taxes.
      - Document, signed: Weimar, to "Dem Stadt Rathe ... Weimar", 1783 Mar 22 (Box 10, Folder 312)
        Goethe, in his capacity as Fürstl.
        Sächs. Kriegs Commissar, signs a
        document for the arrest of a
        deserter, Johann Heinrich Scherf.
      - Document, signed, Weimar, 1809 Jul 27 (Box 10, Folder 313)
        5 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
        Official impressed seal attached
        and with red seal.
        A contract establishing a pension for
        the two sons of Carl Ludwig Fernow,
        who are under the guardianship of
        Carl Bertuch.
        Co-signed by G. Voigt, Carl Bertuch,
        and von Wolfskeel.
      - Power of attorney for Christiane von Goethe, Weimar, 1809 Oct 14 (Box 10, Folder 314)
        With notarization by von Wolfskeel,
        dated Oct. 16, 1809; with impressed
        seal attached.
        Conferring full rights upon Goethe's
        wife to act for him in settling the
        estate of his deceased mother
        Katharina Elisabeth Goethe. As
        assistant in this matter he appoints
        Friedrich Johann Heinrich Schlosser.
      - Receipt, signed, Weimar, 1791 Sep 30 (Box 10, Folder 315)
        Receipt from Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach,
        Bergwerks-Commission.
        Signed, J.W.v. Goethe, and C.G. Voigt.
      - Receipt, signed, Weimar, 1797 Sep 16 (Box 10, Folder 316)
        1 p.; 9 x 16 cm.
        Signed by J.W.v. Goethe, G. Voigt,
        J.G. Seeger.
  - GOETHE, OTTILIE (VON POGWISCH) VON, 1796-1872